In this video, we'll look at how to build terrain using the
Unity Terrain Tools package and the
Universal Render Pipeline. The
Terrain Tools are an excellent way to create high-performance worlds for many platforms with exceptional flexibility and
creative freedom. They work in
conjunction with other Unity systems and serve as an entry point
to creating various types of games and simulations.
Once you're familiar with the Terrain Tools, you'll see that it's a
fantastic way to build worlds. It
provides many features to define your project style and create highly polished scenes. To get started with the
latest Terrain Tools in Unity 2020.1, you
need to make sure your Package Manager is set to enable preview packages. This is under
[Project Settings] > [Package
Manager] > [Advanced Settings]. In
this demo, we'll also install several other
free terrain assets from the Asset Store.
Check the description for a list of these packages. Once you've
installed the Terrain Tools, you can
start building terrain.
Select [Window] > [Terrain] > [TerrainToolbox].
Dock the Terrain Toolbox and
go to the [Create New Terrain] tab. The
tab shows you setting options such as size, height, and starting position. Let's
create one terrain with all the default settings at the
bottom of the window.
Clicking [Create] will
display a new terrain in your scene Raising and
lowering the terrain is the most important component for editing it
using the terrain mesh selected in the Hierarchy window
Make sure the Inspector is displayed
At the top of the terrain component you will see
several icons The
brush icon allows you to
directly edit the terrain geometry texture
Below the row of icons
Click the dropdown and select [Raise or
Lower Terrain]
Select a simple round brush mask
Now you are ready to modify the mesh Let's
create some basic hills and raised areas Without
obvious steps To
create more detailed terrain The
terrain tool supports 16-bit depth brushes
Many of them are
included in the terrain tool sample asset pack
Links are provided in the description
Here is an example of a working brush
Holding down A on your keyboard
adjusts the strength of the sculpt brush
S changes the size of the brush D rotates the brush Holding down
Shift
changes the brush's behavior to smoothing Holding down
Ctrl inverts the brush Let's
lower the terrain with a brush mask instead of raising it
If you want to change these keybindings, you can
use Unity's shortcut manager to rebound
Using a noise brush  You can
create a lot of high-frequency detail across the terrain. You can
add a little randomness to the terrain mesh. The
latest terrain tools also include an erosion brush that
can simulate the effects of wind, water, and heat changes on the mesh. When
used in combination with other brush parameters, you
can create a lot of very realistic effects.
Digging further into the tools,
we polished the mask filters.
These powerful brush filters allow you to
parameterize strokes and
create multi-layer inputs that make it easy to create dynamic effects.
Once you have the terrain and feel that the rough placement of the features is right, let's
move on to texturing.
One of the great things about the Unity terrain workflow is that once you have a
good understanding of the texture system, you can
easily iterate, adjust, and improve any part of the mesh at any time. You can
then start refining and bring your
scene to life.
Creating a palette of terrain materials in the Layers tab
greatly simplifies painting the terrain.
"Experience speaks for itself," but it is important to understand that the
order of textures can be easily changed.
However, if the
order of terrain meshes is changed after you have started texturing, you may encounter
visual problems.
Having a palette prepared in advance
allows you to easily revert materials. In
case you make a mistake,
keep the order of materials in mind.
When painting textures, you need to understand that you are actually painting weighted indices
onto a splatmap.
URP's terrain shader
can blend between an unlimited number of terrain layers;
however, with height-based blending enabled,
Unity supports four terrain layers and one splatmap. You can
save texture palettes as presets to
easily set up terrain meshes with similar biomes and features. The
terrain material itself is a
custom material type that supports albedo, normal mapping, and a special mask texture with multiple features. The
mask texture supports metallic
values ​​in the red channel,
ambient occlusion values ​​in the green channel,
height values ​​which greatly improve material blending in the
blue channel, and
smoothness values ​​in the alpha channel.
If you choose not to include a mask channel, there are
metallic and smoothness overrides for the entire material. The
height value only affects the material if height-based blending is enabled.
Crucial to the appearance of the material is the tiling setting, which
includes texture size and offset, offset based on a
scalar amount related to texture size.
Once the basic setup is complete, you can
start defining features. In
this example, we are creating a temperate forest,
set on a gentle hill with clearly defined paths.  There's
greenwash to define areas that are mainly covered in trees, and also
areas that are covered in moss. For
the darkest and wettest parts of the scene, there are
rocky patches that gather at the bottom of a watershed, cliff patches for more vertical sections of
terrain where grass and moss are less likely to grow,
and some muddy and soily materials.
For sections with more foot movement, such as people and wildlife, there are
damp and depressions at the edges and
dry and cracked textures in the middle.
Whatever type of scene you are creating, you want to
think like nature and
take into account how the basic elements interact with the terrain. Ask yourself where
the sun hits, where the water flows, where the rocks roll.
Combined with quality references, you can really begin to understand the
logical and harmonious relationships between the scene elements. The
next step to make the scene more believable, with the terrain together with the textures underneath, is to
add trees and other vegetation to the terrain. In the
terrain component,
here we go from the brush palette to the tree palette.
First click [Edit Trees].
Add some speed trees. There
is also a link in the description box.
Since we are building this scene for the desktop
Select the Broadleaf and Conifer desktops as source models.
Before placing the trees,
increase the random size range and
uncheck the lock width and height to add
more variation to the tree silhouettes. Make sure to
keep the values ​​within a reasonable range
so you don't notice any unnatural deformations of the trunks and branches.
Next,
select the broadleaf tree prefab from the tree palette.
Click the Mass Place Trees button and
quickly add it to the terrain. A
dialog box will appear with the number of trees for a 250,000 cubic meter zone.
1,500 to 2,000 trees is
roughly the right number for a healthy forest in this vast area. If you use the primary directional light with the
first tree type added, the
trees will have very strong black shadows, which is
usually undesirable visually.
This
happens because the URP does not support global illumination or reflection probes for trees. To mitigate this, add some directional bounce lights
as children of the primary directional light.
These will help reduce the obvious strong shadows and
enhance the shapes beneath the trees.
Make sure the overall value of the light tone is low to match the overall color of the terrain. Make some changes
to the size and density of the tree brush.
Then you can move around within the terrain mesh,
rearrange the trees, and control your clicks to remove trees
from undesirable locations. You can
use normal click strokes to
add trees where they weren't before.
Once you have the deciduous trees arranged as you like, you can
select conifers and add variety to your forest
with this combination of shapes. In
your own work, you might
want to experiment with different tree combinations at various stages of maturity, but even just
these two variations will
give you a nice look. Once the
trees are done and the area around the path is neatly shaped, you
can move on to the grass system for the final touches. In the
demo, we'll keep it simple and
use billboards of grass and flower textures.
Add them to the palette, and once that's
done, the
workflow is similar to painting the tree arrangement.
Variety is important so you don't make sections too dense. You need enough vegetation to
break up the tree trunks and bring the
shape of the hills to life. Even
pops of color with flowers or
drier-colored grass will make the
whole scene much more vibrant without much overhead.
This is where references from photographs and paintings help
guide your arrangement and
find the best places to densely place the billboards.
Unity also supports detail meshes,
so you can create
fully 3D leaves and rocks in a very dynamic way.  You can add other items to the terrain. Once
all the setup is complete and the basic form is finished, you can now spend some time actually moving around in the scene using all the tools we've introduced to
polish the scene to a higher level and
start testing potential gameplay. Once
the world is set up, you
can quickly add a wind zone to bring the trees to life.
Keep the settings low,
otherwise it will look like a hurricane simulation.
Detail can be very impressive.
Add similarly detailed post-processing to improve the final image quality and
ensure you get the mood you want.
Take some time to look around your creation in play mode and evaluate
what you've been able to create using the terrain tools. For more
information about terrain tools, please
see the link below.
Thank you for watching.